<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://fooltowise.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://fooltowise.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-12-13T20:19:19+01:00</updated><id>https://fooltowise.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">From Fool to Wise</title><subtitle>My journey towards worldly wisdom</subtitle><entry><title type="html">What is Financial Independence?</title><link href="https://fooltowise.com/What-is-Financial-Independence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Financial Independence?" /><published>2019-12-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://fooltowise.com/What-is-Financial-Independence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fooltowise.com/What-is-Financial-Independence/">&lt;p&gt;As every journey starts somewhere, mine began when I discovered the concept of Financial Independence (See &lt;a href=&quot;/about.html&quot;&gt;About&lt;/a&gt;). As such, this is the perfect topic to kickstart this website! What is Financial Independence? How do we define it? How to reach it? How long does it take?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow me down the rabbit hole.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go with a broad definition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Financial Independence is about accumulating enough wealth to live without having to work for money anymore. Your assets generate enough cash to cover your expenses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. If you have assets generating an income superior to your expenses, you are financially independent!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it can come with all sorts of flavors… Some will want to be wealthy enough to afford to pay all their luxuries. Others will be happy with cash flows covering only their basic needs (housing, health, food and transportation). Most flavors are between these two broad categories. (Side Note: Financial Independence is often abbreviated FI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the concept has been there for a long time, it really took off around 2010 when blogs such as  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mrmoneymustache.com/&quot;&gt;Mr Money Mustache&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://earlyretirementextreme.com/&quot;&gt;Early Retirement Extreme&lt;/a&gt; started documenting how to reach financial independence. What made people really interested in the topic was that often these bloggers had reached FI &lt;em&gt;in a dozen of years or less&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Switzerland (my home country), the two most famous blogs on the subject are the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mustachianpost.com/&quot;&gt;Mustachian Post&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://retireinprogress.com/&quot;&gt;Retire in Progress&lt;/a&gt;. Go visit them if you are interested on the subject!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-you-reach-financial-independence&quot;&gt;How do you reach Financial Independence?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will assume that you are not a playing in the NBA, you did not win the lottery, you did not inherit from a wealthy distant uncle or what-not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reaching FI is actually simple and can be summarized in three step:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spend less than you earn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invest the difference in productive assets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Repeat until these assets are producing enough income to cover your expenses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said, very simple, right? Simple, &lt;em&gt;but not easy&lt;/em&gt;. Let’s dig deaper into these steps…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-spend-less-than-you-earn&quot;&gt;1) Spend less than you earn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the most important step of all. If you want to have some money to invest, it needs to come from somewhere. And this somewhere is really nothing special, it is just the money that is left after you paid all your expenses… in other words, your savings!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why it is critical to spend way less than you earn and to maximize your savings. You will never be able to own enough assets if you do not save enough money. While general personal finance websites would recommand that you save at least 10% of your earnings, we will see later that it is way too low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be able to reach Financial Independence in a reasonable time, I’d advise to start saving at least &lt;strong&gt;40% of your income, or even 50-60%&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Saving half of my income? But that is strictly impossible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is certainly not easy, most people in the FI community manage to save this kind of money by using two strategies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be mindful about your expenses&lt;/strong&gt;, especially recurring expenses such as the Big 4: Housing, Health, Food and Transportation. These four items take usually the biggest part of your budget, so it is time to be smart about them, minimizing them, while not feeling like an hermit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increase your income&lt;/strong&gt;. While reducing expenses is certainly needed, there is one point after which we run into diminishing returns. That’s when it is time to increase your income: change job, do a side hustle, create a small business, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being more specific about saving money would fill many other posts. But the main lesson is this: &lt;em&gt;Save as much as you can, so you can start investing your hard-earned savings into productive assets.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-invest-the-difference-in-productive-assets&quot;&gt;2) Invest the difference in productive assets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have started saving a significant amount of money, it is time to start investing it in productive assets. There are two important words in this sentence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;investing&quot;&gt;Investing:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to clarify first what I mean by investing. The word has many meanings in our culture, so it’s time to be accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investing is about renouncing now to a certain amount of purchasing power, in the hope to receive back more purchasing power in the future.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, let’s see two or three examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buying a car, while often expensive, is not an investment. Its value depreciate quickly over time and is never gained back. It could be an investment if you use the car to perform activities that brings in significant money (ex: you buy a truck and transform it in food truck.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By the same token, just because something is expensive does not mean it is an investment. You need to have reasonable hope of at least getting back your purchasing power to name it that way. Think about it the next time a friend tells you he &lt;em&gt;invested&lt;/em&gt; in this brand new TV-set.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On the other hand, buying a diversified portfolio of shares with a long term horizon, has historically proven to generate a compounded return of 7% to 8 % per annum. After 10 years, such a portfolio will double in value. That’s what i call an improved purchasing power!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;productive-assets&quot;&gt;Productive Assets:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we are clear with the meaning of &lt;em&gt;investing&lt;/em&gt;, you need to figure out in what to invest your savings. There are many different assets available, and this can be very confusing. But as a rule of thumb, invest in productive assets, i.e. assets whose underlyings are producing cash flows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As we have seen, stocks are productive assets. They represent a shared ownership in a business, and this business is supposed to make profits by selling goods or services to customers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rental Real Estate is a productive asset: it generates cash flows to the owner by renting the housing unit to a tenant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gold is not really a productive asset. It has a nice property: it keeps its value. Over the long term, an ounce of gold in 1800 provided as much purchasing power as an ounce of gold now. There are of course fluctuations in between, but you get the picture. The downside of gold is that over the long term it won’t really increase your purchasing power&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cryptocurrencies are not (yet) productive assets. We haven’t found yet a stable way to use crypto-currencies that would entice customers to pay for. Sure, the value of Bitcoin and Co. has fluctuated a lot in the last few years. But at this stage it is still more speculation than a true productive asset.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-repeat-until-your-assets-are-producing-enough-cash-to-cover-your-expenses&quot;&gt;3) Repeat until your assets are producing enough cash to cover your expenses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much is enough to cover your needs? There is a lot of debates on the exact amount, but the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trinity_study&quot;&gt;Trinity Study&lt;/a&gt;  is a good starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published in 1998, the study defines a “safe withdrawal rate”, equal to 4% of your assets. Imagine someone withdrawing only 4% of his funds every year, while keeping the rest invested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;According to the study, such a person would have a 97% chance of never running out of money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gave birth to the &lt;em&gt;4% rule&lt;/em&gt; :  to be financially free your annual expenses should be less than 4% of your capital. Another way to state it is that your capital should be worth at least 25 times your annual expenses (because 25 = 1/4%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is currently a lot of controversy about the validity of the Trinity Study, and people usually recommend to be a bit more conservative a save up to 33 times your annual expenses. For more details, you can consult the outstanding work of &lt;a href=&quot;https://earlyretirementnow.com/2016/12/07/the-ultimate-guide-to-safe-withdrawal-rates-part-1-intro/&quot;&gt;Early Retirement Now&lt;/a&gt; on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But yeah, if you don’t want to overcomplicate things, target a capital equal to around 25 and 30 times your annual spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you know what is your target, this opens the room for many questions! How long does it take? How much should you save? What is the impact of the yield of your assets?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hem. It’s time for some maths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(if you are maths-phobic, you can directly jump to the remarks.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-maths-behind-all-of-that&quot;&gt;The maths behind all of that&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let’s call C0 your initial capital (i.e your current savings).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each year, you will save an amount S.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your annual expenses are E. You will thus want to reach an capital target T equal to 25 * E&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your investments have a yearly rate of return of r%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s call C(n) your capital at year n. Obviously, C(0) is equal to C0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After one year, C0 is invested in productive assets returning r%, and you have saved as well an additional S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C(1) = (1+r)  C_0 + S&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same way, after an additional year, C(1) had returns of r%, and you saved yet another S&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C(2) = (1+r)  C(1) + S = (1+r)  [ (1+r)  C_0 + S ] + S&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C(n+1) = (1+r)  C(n) + S&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can show by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mathematical_induction&quot;&gt;mathematical induction&lt;/a&gt; that C(n) can be rewritten:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C(n) = (1+r) ^n  (C_0 + \frac {S}{r})  - \frac {S}{r}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At year N, C(N) reaches the target capital T ( equal to 25 times E)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C(N) = T = (1+r) ^N  (C0 + \frac {S}{r})  - \frac {S}{r}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solving for N, we get:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;N =  \frac  {\ln(  \frac  {T +\frac {S}{r}}  {(C_0 + \frac {S}{r}}) }{ \ln (1+r) }&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. If you start without any capital, you can simplify with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;N =  \frac  {\ln( 1 + \frac  {r T }{S} )}  { \ln (1+r) }&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing that    $ \frac{T}{S} =  \frac {25 E}{S}$   , we can introduce the concept of saving rate, which is equal to the ratio between your savings and your revenues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\sigma = \frac {Savings}{Revenues} = \frac {Savings}{Savings + Expenses } = \frac {S}{S + E }&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We show that   $ \frac{E}{S} =  (\frac {1}{\sigma} - 1) $&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and thus, our final result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;N =  \frac  {\ln( 1 + 25 r (\frac  {1 }{\sigma}-1))}  { \ln (1+r) }&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;remarks&quot;&gt;Remarks:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It does not look like a lot but it is actually huge. Knowing only your investment yield and your saving rate (i.e how much of your revenue are you saving), you can figure out how long it takes to be financially independent. Nothing else matters except these two variables!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s see how long it takes to reach FI with different values of investment yields and saving rates:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/NSavingRate.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Results&quot; /&gt;
Someone saving half of his income and investing it at a 10% annual rate will be financially independent in 13 years. With the same annual returns, someone saving only 10% of his income will only reach financial freedom in 33 years! This is not a reasonable timeframe. Even less so if annual returns are less than 10%… The time needed to reach FI jumps then very quickly to over 50 years…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As you can see, the two conditions needed to reach financial freedom within 15 years are an annual investment returns of more than 5% and a saving rate of more than 50%!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s enough theory for today, dear reader!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spend way less that you earn, invest the difference in productive assets, rinse and repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s only the starting point. I discovered quickly that I would soon be asking more qualitative questions…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>julien</name></author><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">As every journey starts somewhere, mine began when I discovered the concept of Financial Independence (See About). As such, this is the perfect topic to kickstart this website! What is Financial Independence? How do we define it? How to reach it? How long does it take?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fooltowise.com/assets/images/ParrotLong.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://fooltowise.com/assets/images/ParrotLong.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>