<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://fooltowise.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://fooltowise.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-01-04T12:46:43+01:00</updated><id>https://fooltowise.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">From Fool to Wise</title><subtitle>My journey towards worldly wisdom</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Your Brain 101 - Part 2: Two Thinking Systems</title><link href="https://fooltowise.com/Your-Brain-101-Part-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Your Brain 101 -  Part 2: Two Thinking Systems" /><published>2019-12-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://fooltowise.com/Your-Brain-101-Part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fooltowise.com/Your-Brain-101-Part-2/">&lt;p&gt;This is second part of my series of articles on how the brain works. In the last part, &lt;a href=&quot;/Your-Brain-101-Part-1&quot;&gt;we saw how neurons work and how they interact&lt;/a&gt;. We also so a model of how they are organized in three “layers” in the brain.
In this part I want to present the works of Nobel Prize laureate Daniel Kahneman and the late Amos Tversky. They have shown that our brain often behaves as if two agents with wildly differing characteristics were in control. Most of what I will talk about is sourced from the excellent book &lt;em&gt;Thinking, Fast and Slow&lt;/em&gt; by Daniel Kahneman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;two-modes-of-thoughts&quot;&gt;Two modes of thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often believe that we know what is going on in our mind. We experience one thought, which leads to another one in a logical manner, and so on. We would even be aware of all our thoughts. But this is only one type of thinking happening into our brain, and not even the most common one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To prove his point, Kahneman takes the example of the below picture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Angry.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;angry&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Thinking, fast and slow, Daniel Kahneman&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Automatically, our brain has picked up a lot of small cues from the face of the woman to know that she is angry, and that she is likely to yell not very nice things to us. This happened effortlessly, without you trying conscientiously to actively decipher the mood of the woman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now solve the following multiplication:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;17 * 24&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will notice that your mental experience is vastly different. First, the result did not come automatically to you.  You are allocated a lot of conscious effort to perform the calculus, in a slow, organized and methodic way. It is likely you stopped everything you were doing to solve the multiplication. &lt;sup&gt;(1)&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how Kahneman introduces the concept of two agents, System 1 and System 2, who are the principal characters of our mental life. System 1 is responsible for “fast” thinking (as happened with the angry woman), while System 2 handles Slow, deliberate thinking (the multiplication example).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;system-1-fast-automatic-thinking&quot;&gt;System 1: Fast, automatic thinking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you saw the woman above, your System 1 took over to process all the information given by the situation (duh, she looks very angry! I bet she is not going to be nice to me…). System 1 operates automatically, quickly and effortlessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, we cannot have any control over it. When looking at the woman, we could not “not see” on purpose that she is angry. Even if we order our brain to ignore the woman, it will figure out her mood anyway.  We have no control over System 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kahneman gives a list of activities that are typically performed by System 1:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;detect that one object is more distant than another&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;orient to the source of a sudden sound&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;detect hostility in a voice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Answer to “2 + 2 = ?”  (simple math question)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make pattern associations, like figuring out that a “meek and tidy soul with a passion for detail” fits more the character of a librarian than ta farmer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these tasks require no effort, they are performed routinely by System 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A drawback of System 1 is that it cannot be turned off. Whatever happens to you, it will continuously process its environment on the fly. If you see a word on a billboard that you already know, you will read it, unless your attention is totally depleted (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;system-2-slow-deliberate-thinking&quot;&gt;System 2: Slow, deliberate thinking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now comes the laborious System 2. When we think of ourselves, this is the system we have in mind. System 2 handles effortful mental activities like complex computations or problem solving. We often think of System 2 as the part of our brain responsible for agency, choice and concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The common point of all activities performed by System 2 is that they require attention. Draw away the attention, and they get badly disrupted. Kahneman gives another list of examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on the voice of a particular person in a noisy room in a party&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remember a phone number&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Park in a narrow space&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fill out a tax form&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check the validity of a complex logical argument&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An outstanding feature of System 2 is that the more cognitively demanding a task is, the less attention we are going to pay to anything else, until we become blind to our environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may already know the below video. If you don’t, good. In a now famous experiment done by Chabris and Simons, the two researchers created a short film showing two teams playing basketball. One team wears white t-shirts, while the other teams wears black t-shirts. In the experiment, the viewer of the video were asked count how many passes the white team would make. In a normal setting, this task is totally absorbing and cognitively demanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video is here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe style=&quot;width:100%;&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vJG698U2Mvo?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thousands viewed the video, but only half of them noticed the gorilla while counting the passes. And the gorilla was present in the movie for nine full seconds! It is not an exaggeration to state that cognitively difficult tasks can blind us to our environment…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This phenomena happens as well in what we call &lt;em&gt;ego depletion&lt;/em&gt; : suppose you have to perform a cognitive - heavy task like remembering 7 numbers in your memory for several minutes. After the task is realized, you could believe that your mind is ready to tackle any new cognitive challenge. But studies revealed that as long as your mind is not rested, if any other difficult task arise (like choosing between a healthy salad and a caloric cookie), your System 2 will not be able to perform at its maximum capacity: it is very likely that you will indulge on the cookie. Cognitive performance is a limited resource, and as such the brain cannot be strained 100% of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has a big consequence on your will and self-control: those are tiring activities, and &lt;strong&gt;I guarantee you that having to control yourself all the time is doomed to fail at some point.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-lazy-controller&quot;&gt;A lazy controller&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we know that System 2 cannot always continuously perform difficult tasks. In fact, most of the time it will prefer low-efforts tasks. It is a recurring theme of nature that the path-of-least-effort gets often rewarded, and System 2 is no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;System 2 is an enormous consumer of glucose. It looks like “cognitively demanding” is actually a synonym for “energy demanding”, as researchers have monitored the amount of glucose the brain consumes, and figured out that its cognition performed better when the glucose levels in the human body where restored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many systems in nature, System 2 is energy efficient: if it can escape a demanding effort, it will. Therefore, most of the time it will be engaged in a low effort mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we become skilled in a task, the connections within the brain get reinforced and System 2 will consume less and less energy to perform the task. At some point, it will become totally automatic and get transferred to System 1. That’s what happens when we learn how to walk: a baby has to focus intensely when performing his first steps, but for an adult it is a second nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-do-the-two-systems-interact&quot;&gt;How do the two Systems interact?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I have presented them in a separate manner, there is no reason to think the the two systems operate separately. Both Systems are always on, provided we are awake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their binomial setup, System 1 will continuously generate ideas for System 2: ideas, impressions, intentions, feelings. &lt;strong&gt;If they get validated by System 2, these impressions are then transformed into beliefs, upon which we take action if needed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this goes smoothly most of the time. System 2 adopts the suggestions of System 1, and all is well in the best of the worlds, because most of the time we believe our impressions. Not doing so would be excruciating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as soon as System 1 runs into difficulties, it will call System 2 to comes to the rescue. The multiplication above is a good example. System 1 is incapable of processing tasks in an organized way, so when it needs to do so it will outsource the task to System 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another trigger for outsourcing is when System 1 notices something unusual or which runs into conflict with its model of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a cat barks or a gorilla crosses a basketball court, System 1 will get confused enough to call System 2 for further analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we have a basic understanding of how the two systems interact. Most of the time, System 1 is actually doing all the work and its suggestions are stamped as “approved” by System 2. It is only when System 1 is overwhelmed that System 2 will take over and do the leg work. But as we have also seen, System 2 can be lazy. Sometimes, it will not control what System 1 generated and just accept it “as is”. This is often the cause of many cognitive errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, let’s not be to alarmist: this arrangement works well in most situations! This quick and “economic” structure is very efficient from an evolution point of view and there is no doubt that it gave us many advantages over other species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s sum up what we know so far:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;System 1 is the automatic ideas, associations and links generator, and System 2 is the validator, able to organize itself to come to a conclusion.  System 1 is intuitive and impulsive, while System 2 is capable of reasoning and being cautious, while sometimes being lazy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since System 1 is so important to how our mind works, let’s dig deeper to see some of its additional features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-associative-machine&quot;&gt;The Associative Machine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that System 1 works automatically and effortlessly, but what does it do exactly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Associations. System 1 works mainly by making associations. Neurons fired by System 1 will trigger other neurons that are linked to it. All those neurons have the common point of being somehow related because they represent related concepts. These neurons themselves trigger other neurons linked to yet other related concepts, and so on in a snowball effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each idea is connected to other ideas as long as they are coherent between themselves. An element will strengthen related coherent elements, supported by the architecture of underlying neuronal connections. A word can elicit memories, that trigger emotions, movements and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This whole process is called associative activation: provided that there is some relatedness between two concepts, the activation of one concept will surely activate the other. An activated idea does not merely activate one another idea, but many others, which in turn activate in cascade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all of this happens without us even being aware of it! System 2 may focus on one or two elements activated by System 1, but System 1 is working relentlessly to generate new associations as soon as an idea is triggered. Only a few of the activated ideas will register in consciousness; most of the associative work is silent and below the radar or our conscious selves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kahneman gives the example of the two following words:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bananas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vomit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although in general the two terms are unrelated, as soon as they are read System 1 cannot refrain from generating associations that could link the two words. Especially, the mind will create automatically a temporal sequence - without being told so - where the fruits caused the sickness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same time, a small feeling of disgust was triggered, the body tensed and the heart rate increased… It is as if the whole body had experienced a lesser intensity version of the story, just by reading those two words! Without us being aware, System 1 has generated all the elements, ideas, emotions and actions where those two juxtaposed words made sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would System 1 do that? Because in most cases, it is very helpful and efficient! Imagine a machine that in the majority of situations can induce the context of any situation by looking at a few elements. That is exactly what System 1 did here! It informs us about the past and prepare us for the future. All of this with the very few elements available (here, only two words!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This associative machine leads us to the psychological concept of &lt;em&gt;priming&lt;/em&gt;. As activated ideas trigger other ideas, beliefs, emotions and behaviors, we could expect that we could make people more receptive to other ideas by activating related concepts. And this is exactly what experiences show…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subjects having seen the word “Wash” are more likely to guess “SOAP” when seeing “SO_P”. Other subjects having seen “Eat” will instead fill “SO_P” with SOUP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making people more receptive to one concept by showing them related concepts is called &lt;em&gt;priming&lt;/em&gt;. For example, subjects primed with money-related concepts reported a more independent mindset as well as a more pronounced problem solving attitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all sounds frightening. We all have in mind scenarios where evil marketers or snake oil salesmen could use some variants of priming to make us more receptive to their scam products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it happens in reality, we have to realize that absolutely &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; primes us. By reading the above paragraph, you have been primed with concepts related to scams, and surely you experienced a bit of disgust and thought of other occasions where scammers tried to get your money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Absolutely everything primes us then, and this is why it is very important to take care of the environment surrounding us. It is easy to get primed by factors we would like to avoid, so they should not enter our life in the first place. In particular (and I will talk a lot about it on this website) avoid the news like the plague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But associations and priming are not the only features of System 1. Let’s see how it processes information based on its cognitive ease and familiarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fooled-by-cognitive-ease&quot;&gt;Fooled by Cognitive Ease&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we have seen earlier, the brain is made of billions of neurons connected to each other. When a connection between two neurons is activated, it becomes stronger: the strength of the signal increases and more synapses (the connections between dendrites and axons) are likely to be created between the neurons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wiring has a consequence on how the brain processes concepts. The more the brain encounters a concept, the stronger the underlying neuronal connections become, and the easier the concept will be to retrieve next time we access it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;em&gt;ease&lt;/em&gt; is fundamental here: the easier it is to retrieve a concept, the less the effort done by the brain to by the brain and the less strain on System 1. But what happens next is intrinsic to System 1: the less strain it experiences, the more “familiar” it is with the idea, &lt;strong&gt;and it considers it more and more credible.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can happen in many different forms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;having a repeated experience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;having been primed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;being in a good mood&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/cognitive_ease.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;angry&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Thinking, fast and slow, Daniel Kahneman&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This intrinsic wiring of System 1 has thus a very peculiar behavior: &lt;strong&gt;it equals ease of cognition with familiarity and truth.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would that be? Once again, because it is the most efficient tradeoff between being one hundred percent right and expanding countless amounts of glucose energy and time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, ideas and concepts that repeat themselves are true: apples fall down from the tree and not toward the tree branch, 2+2 is always equal to 4 (and the more it is repeated, the more we are getting comfortable with its truth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, politicians and unscrupulous marketers have understood this since a long time. In reality, repeating a lie for a time long enough does not make the lie become the truth. &lt;em&gt;But in your brain, it does!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said earlier, System 1 only calls System 2 for help when it is either confused, detect an anomaly or it cannot process the cognitive load of a given task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a given sentence is repeated again and again, System 1 will thus trust it more and more, and never call System 2 to the rescue. This is where many of our biases come from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Confirmation bias: we only seek the facts that confirm a belief. As these facts are likely to be already stored in our brain, they are easier to retrieve. Furthermore, contrarian facts will impose cognitive strain on the brain, and System 2 will surely have to work hard. But we know that System 2 works hard only parsimoniously!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recency and Saliency bias: events that just happened are easier to recall than older facts. It works the same with vivid memories. As a result, these facts are usually more familiar and thus “truer” than other facts. For instance, more people are worried about plane crashes compared to car crashes because the former is more spectacular, and when it happens, news channels make sure to report it again and again and again. Car crashes are much more mundane and thus less reported, less salient. But when we look at the crashes statistics &lt;sup&gt;(2)&lt;/sup&gt;, the results are clear: you should be way more worried about dying in a car crash (odds of 1 to 114) than in a plane crash (odds of 1 to 9’821). Dying in a plane crash is 85 times less likely!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Availability bias, also called “What you see is all there is”: When you see a text, a thesis, or a given context, the elements laying in front of your eyes are much easier to take into account that what is not there. As a result, &lt;em&gt;we tend to weight what is present more than what is absent.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But once again, we should not be mad about it, because most of the time our brain works just fine. On the other hand, we should be aware of such shortcomings so we can try to avoid stepping into cognitive situations where we would be easily tricked…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it for the 2 agents model of our brain made famous by the works of Kahneman and Tversky! We have constantly two kinds of circuitry running in our brain:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One that is very fast, effortless, working mainly by associations and judging by cognitive ease: System 1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Another that is slow, deliberate, lazy and which consumes a lot of energy: our System 2, to which we often refer when talking about “reason”, “will”, or “self-control”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;System 1 runs continuously and generates a flow of ideas that System 2 can then approve or reject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;System 1 and System 2 use shortcuts so that we can have a very good tradeoff between accuracy and energy consumption. This has been a superb advantage from an evolution point of view against other species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But doing so comes at a cost, and sometimes System 1 and System 2 can be tricked, both in their own ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;System 1 can judge familiar concepts more likely to be true&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;System 1 will be more open to generate ideas linked to a given idea if it has been “primed” with a similar idea beforehand&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is only so much that System 2 can monitor: cognitive problems are very consuming, both in energy, attention and willpower. As a result, a busy System 2 can become totally blind to its surrounding. A strained System 2 will also perform poorly on its next cognitive task, hence a big need to rest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(1) The result is 408, by the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(2) &lt;a href=&quot;https://fortune.com/2017/07/20/are-airplanes-safer-than-cars/&quot;&gt;https://fortune.com/2017/07/20/are-airplanes-safer-than-cars/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>julien</name></author><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">This is second part of my series of articles on how the brain works. In the last part, we saw how neurons work and how they interact. We also so a model of how they are organized in three “layers” in the brain. In this part I want to present the works of Nobel Prize laureate Daniel Kahneman and the late Amos Tversky. They have shown that our brain often behaves as if two agents with wildly differing characteristics were in control. Most of what I will talk about is sourced from the excellent book Thinking, Fast and Slow by Daniel Kahneman.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fooltowise.com/assets/images/ThinkingFastSlowLong.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://fooltowise.com/assets/images/ThinkingFastSlowLong.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Your Brain 101 - Part 1 - Anatomy</title><link href="https://fooltowise.com/Your-Brain-101-Part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Your Brain 101 - Part 1 - Anatomy" /><published>2019-12-18T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://fooltowise.com/Your-Brain-101-Part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fooltowise.com/Your-Brain-101-Part-1/">&lt;p&gt;Your brain is the place where all your decisions take place. For this reason, it is important to have a good idea of how the brain works so we can take good decisions and live a good life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of what follows has been inspired by the excellent book &lt;em&gt;Behave: The biology of humans at our best and worst&lt;/em&gt;, by Robert Sapolsky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: I am aware that what follows may be a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; simplification of how the brain actually works. But I still think it is a very useful model…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is the brain made of?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;neurons-and-transmitters&quot;&gt;Neurons and Transmitters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;neuron-basics&quot;&gt;Neuron basics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brain and the nervous system are principally made of two kind of cells: neurons and glial cells. Neurons are responsible for transmitting information. When you take a decision, neurons are at work. Glial cells supports neurons and provide them with insulation between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s focus on neurons. Your brain contains around 90 billion neurons. Here is what a neuron looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/neuron.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Neuron&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Behave, Robert Sapolsky&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one end of the neuron we find small filaments called dendrites. The dendrites receive information from other neurons. At the other hand is located the axon, which ends in numerous terminals. These terminals will transmit the information to the next neuron, by connecting to his dendrites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The message transmitted by a neuron is an electrical flow. The inside of the membrane of a neuron contains ions (both positive and negative), just like the environment of the neuron. The distribution of these ions will determine the state of the neuron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a simplified summary, a neuron has two states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The resting potential&lt;/em&gt;: this is when the neuron is not excited and has “nothing to say”. Its electrical charge is then negative compared to its environment: -70mV&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the neuron receives a signal through its dendrites, its membrane will open, the ions will change their distribution, and overall the net effect will be that the neuron is more positively charged : +30mV. It is then in a state called &lt;em&gt;Action Potential&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The neuron will thus continuously commute between two states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Action potential: “I have something to say”…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Resting potential: “I have nothing to say”…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the neuron switch to an action potential, this potential propagates along the axon and is transmitted  through the axon terminals to the next neurons’ dendrites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;synapses-activation-and-connections&quot;&gt;Synapses, activation and connections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it gets a bit more difficult: a neuron is not that easily excited! If it receives an excitation signal from another neuron, this signal won’t be enough to switch from a resting potential to an action potential. Instead, its potential will become just a little bit less negative (it will go for instance from -70mV to -60 mV).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to switch to an action potential, the neuron needs to receive excitation signals from many neurons at the same time! It has in effect an activation function : there is a threshold to overcome so that it actually switches. For a signal to be transmitted between neurons, a lot of connections have to be made. And as you can imagine, there are indeed a monstrous number of such connections in the brain: around 100 trillion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk about these connections: between the axon terminals of an emitting neuron and the dendrites of a receiving neuron, there is a space called the &lt;em&gt;synapse&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the synapse, the axon will send chemical compounds called &lt;em&gt;neurotransmitters&lt;/em&gt;, which are received by the dendrites of the receiving neuron. The more neurotransmitters received, the stronger the transmitted signal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these transmitters are actually famous, we will talk about them later: dopamine, serotonin, adrenaline, noradrenaline…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Synapse.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Synapse&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Source: Behave, Robert Sapolsky&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fun fact: you may have heard of Indians from South American hunting with blowpipes and darts poisoned with curare. This poison acts by inhibiting the acetylcholine neurotransmitter. This transmitter is responsible (among other things) for stimulating your diaphragm to contract. Poisoned with curare, the target stop breathing and dies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we have many different neurotransmitters, they have different effects on neurons. In particular, there are transmitters that, instead of increasing the potential of the neuron (to get closer of the action potential) actually do the opposite. They decrease the potential of the receiving neuron, and make it harder for him to get activated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The important consequence of this is that some neurons can inhibit other neurons and we can generalize it to the whole brain! Indeed, some brain parts can inhibit other parts of the brain. When a group of neurons send a signal to activate or inhibit another group of neurons, the mechanism is called a &lt;em&gt;neuronal projection&lt;/em&gt;. We will see next that neuronal projections are the meat and potatoes of how the brain works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, now that we have a basic understanding of how neurons work, let’s have a look at the bigger picture: the brain and its different parts, and how they interact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-three-layered-brain&quot;&gt;The three-layered brain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a fully accurate model of the brain would prove absolutely impossible. Nevertheless, Paul McLean proposed a fascinating model describing the brain in three layers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first and deeper layer, called the reptilian brain (or the brain stem). It is in charge of the heart’s regulation, breathing, perspiration and temperature, as well as various primary needs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The second layer is called the limbic system, and communicates directly with the first layer. The limbic brain is responsible for emotions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The outer and third layer, called the neocortex. It is responsible for cognition, memory, abstraction, language. To get any action done, it needs to communicate with the limbic system, who will in turn communicate with the reptilian brain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/three-layered-brain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Three-layered brain&quot; /&gt;  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-reptilian-brain&quot;&gt;The Reptilian Brain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reptilian brain is in charge of autonomic functions of the body, which are divided in two parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The sympathetic nervous system (SNS), who manages the response of the human body to stressing stimuli (increase of the heart rate, pulmonary rate…) The SNS is absolutely primordial in cases of emergency (If you see a lion, your SNS takes over, increasing your heart rate and optimizing many  variables in your body to perform the sprint of your life). The SNS neurotransmitters are the noradrenaline and the adrenaline.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The parasympathetic nervous system, which on the other hand maintains the body in a state of rest and digestion. Its neurotransmitter is the acetylcholine (whom we met before in the curare example…)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To function properly, the human body needs a good balance between sympathetic and parasympathetic nervous systems, and the reptilian brain is responsible for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What is very important to understand is that any physical action taken by your body has been triggered through your reptilian brain. Either directly, or indirectly from upper layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see an example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a full bladder, the circuitry of your reptilian brain will vote for urinating, which is an autonomic bodily function. Now if you experience something absolutely terrifying, your limbic system (in charge of emotions) will persuade your reptilian brain to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a consequence, emotions can change bodily functions through neuronal projections, and we will see as well how cognition can impact emotions or vice versa. The neocortex and the limbic system have something to say about how your bodily function perform!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-lymbic-system&quot;&gt;The Lymbic System&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we said, the limbic system is the second layer of the brain, responsible for emotions. In particular, let’s focus on an area the size of a small nut, called the amygdala.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core role of the amygdala is to throw alerts when something is off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It certainly comes from the time where our ancestors were living in the Savanah: if something moves in a bush, it is much better to throw an alert through the amygdala (this is a lion!) , run away and think later. In case it was actually a lion, the amygdala saved our life. The guy staying there thinking “Maybe it is a lion, maybe not, i am not sure, let’s check it out” would not have survived and passed its genes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this life-saving feature comes with a lot of drawbacks…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amygdala is preponderant in aggression : when it is stimulated, the aggressivity of an individual increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amygdala is also a central element in experiencing fear, anxiety and incertitude, even in a social context.  For instance, when someone is not sure about how to comply to the social norms of his surroundings, he will experience an activation of his amygdala, which then will do a neuronal projection to the reptilian brain so that the person will show physical signs of anxiety…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A troubling fact about the amygdala is how it processes sensory data (image, sounds, …). The amygdala has access to super fast sensory neural circuitry, but which lacks accuracy. When our eyes see something, the amygdala is usually among the firsts notified (way before the rest of our cognitive circuits).  On the other hand, the amygdala is never really sure of what it saw, since its neural connections lack precision. The picture it receives is blurry and lacking contrast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In high stress environment, this can lead to tragic situations: for instance, the amygdala could decide it is seeing a gun, whereas the cognitive zones of the brain would figure out it is actually a cellphone. Since the amygdala will be the first one to act on the reptilian brain, it is easy to imagine what the consequences could be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the amygdala has also an impact on the outer layer of the brain (the neocortex, see below). For instance, by influencing the part responsible for factual memory (the hippocampus) the brain can learn a fear!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But enough about the amygdala, let’s talk now about the last layer of the brain, in charge of cognitive activities… the neocortex!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-neocortex&quot;&gt;The Neocortex&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outer layer of the brain is called the neocortex. It is the part of the brain we often link to &lt;em&gt;“Rationality”&lt;/em&gt;. In a nutshell, its role is to choose the harder choice when it is the right thing to do. It regulates emotions, masters the impulsivity, organizes the knowledge strategically and then initiates an action based on a decision…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The neocortex is the most recently evolve part of the brain. When we compare a human brain with a primate’s one, the most striking difference will be in the size of the neocortex, and most notably in the pre-frontal cortex (the part located in the front of the brain). The pre-frontal cortex has a role of decider and often chooses between several conflicting choices (for instance, an cognitive decision versus an emotive one). It also has a dominating role in sorting things by categories and creating abstractions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is most active when we focus on a task, or we pay attention to a detail. It will be intensively stimulated as well when we delay gratification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the frontal cortex consumes a lot of energy, especially when it is focusing on something. If we allocate many resources to a cognitive task, the following tasks will be negatively impacted, because the brain does not have access to infinite amounts of energy. &lt;strong&gt;As a direct consequence, willpower is a finite resource!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another limitation: compared to the rest of the brain, the neocortex is quite slow to process information… it is the perfect antagonist of the amygdala: when the neocortex is slow but with highly accurate, the amygdala and the limbic system are super fast, but grossly inaccurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the neocortex is usually able to take the “right” decision by inhibiting the limbic system (remember the neuronal projection inhibiting other neurons!). This forbids the brain to take purely emotional emotions, however we will now see that it is not always the case…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sequence-of-decision&quot;&gt;Sequence of decision&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when the brain is stimulated by an external system, for instance seeing a new picture?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that the quickest to react will be the limbic system, thanks to its very fast circuitry. At this moment, the brain will a rough idea of what is going on and start experiencing emotions, &lt;em&gt;but it is not yet conscious of it&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the information will arrive to the neocortex that will process it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, something weird happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We would expect our brain to be fully rational and to handle in a correct an cognitively accurate the information provided by the signal, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, it is not that simple… The result will unfortunately be very dependent on the focus that we allocate to the processing…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If we are focused and mentally rested, the neocortex will activate, organize knowledge and take a rational decision based on facts, as we would expect.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;But that’s actually not often the case. What happens most of the case is that, being very demanding in energy, the cortex will become lazy, and become influenced by the limbic system. Instead of reasoning rationally, the neocortex will look for a reason to &lt;em&gt;rationalize&lt;/em&gt; the decision that has already been taken by the limbic system…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is huge; most of the time, the human brain is not a rational machine, but a &lt;em&gt;rationalizing&lt;/em&gt; machine!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first case, it starts from the facts to arrive to a conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second case, the brain starts from the conclusion it wants to reach (and dictated by the limbic system), and selects the facts that support this conclusion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, the brain has a built-in confirmation bias mechanism… if we don’t pay attention, we are most likely to only filter arguments that comfort our pre-existing opinions…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Faced with the &lt;strong&gt;choice between changing&lt;/strong&gt; one’s mind and &lt;strong&gt;proving&lt;/strong&gt; that there is no need to do so, almost everyone gets busy on the &lt;strong&gt;proof&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;em&gt;John Kenneth Galbraith&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>julien</name></author><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">Your brain is the place where all your decisions take place. For this reason, it is important to have a good idea of how the brain works so we can take good decisions and live a good life!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fooltowise.com/assets/images/brain101-long.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://fooltowise.com/assets/images/brain101-long.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What is Financial Independence?</title><link href="https://fooltowise.com/What-is-Financial-Independence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is Financial Independence?" /><published>2019-12-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-12-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://fooltowise.com/What-is-Financial-Independence</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://fooltowise.com/What-is-Financial-Independence/">&lt;p&gt;As every journey starts somewhere, mine began when I discovered the concept of Financial Independence (See &lt;a href=&quot;/about.html&quot;&gt;About&lt;/a&gt;). As such, this is the perfect topic to kickstart this website! What is Financial Independence? How do we define it? How to reach it? How long does it take?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow me down the rabbit hole.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s go with a broad definition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Financial Independence is about accumulating enough wealth to live without having to work for money anymore. Your assets generate enough cash to cover your expenses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. If you have assets generating an income superior to your expenses, you are financially independent!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it can come with all sorts of flavors… Some will want to be wealthy enough to afford to pay all their luxuries. Others will be happy with cash flows covering only their basic needs (housing, health, food and transportation). Most flavors are between these two broad categories. (Side Note: Financial Independence is often abbreviated FI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the concept has been there for a long time, it really took off around 2010 when blogs such as  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mrmoneymustache.com/&quot;&gt;Mr Money Mustache&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://earlyretirementextreme.com/&quot;&gt;Early Retirement Extreme&lt;/a&gt; started documenting how to reach financial independence. What made people really interested in the topic was that often these bloggers had reached FI &lt;em&gt;in a dozen of years or less&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Switzerland (my home country), the two most famous blogs on the subject are the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mustachianpost.com/&quot;&gt;Mustachian Post&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://retireinprogress.com/&quot;&gt;Retire in Progress&lt;/a&gt;. Go visit them if you are interested on the subject!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-you-reach-financial-independence&quot;&gt;How do you reach Financial Independence?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will assume that you are not a playing in the NBA, you did not win the lottery, you did not inherit from a wealthy distant uncle or what-not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reaching FI is actually simple and can be summarized in three step:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spend less than you earn&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invest the difference in productive assets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Repeat until these assets are producing enough income to cover your expenses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said, very simple, right? Simple, &lt;em&gt;but not easy&lt;/em&gt;. Let’s dig deaper into these steps…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-spend-less-than-you-earn&quot;&gt;1) Spend less than you earn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the most important step of all. If you want to have some money to invest, it needs to come from somewhere. And this somewhere is really nothing special, it is just the money that is left after you paid all your expenses… in other words, your savings!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why it is critical to spend way less than you earn and to maximize your savings. You will never be able to own enough assets if you do not save enough money. While general personal finance websites would recommand that you save at least 10% of your earnings, we will see later that it is way too low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be able to reach Financial Independence in a reasonable time, I’d advise to start saving at least &lt;strong&gt;40% of your income, or even 50-60%&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Saving half of my income? But that is strictly impossible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is certainly not easy, most people in the FI community manage to save this kind of money by using two strategies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be mindful about your expenses&lt;/strong&gt;, especially recurring expenses such as the Big 4: Housing, Health, Food and Transportation. These four items take usually the biggest part of your budget, so it is time to be smart about them, minimizing them, while not feeling like an hermit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increase your income&lt;/strong&gt;. While reducing expenses is certainly needed, there is one point after which we run into diminishing returns. That’s when it is time to increase your income: change job, do a side hustle, create a small business, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being more specific about saving money would fill many other posts. But the main lesson is this: &lt;em&gt;Save as much as you can, so you can start investing your hard-earned savings into productive assets.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-invest-the-difference-in-productive-assets&quot;&gt;2) Invest the difference in productive assets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have started saving a significant amount of money, it is time to start investing it in productive assets. There are two important words in this sentence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;investing&quot;&gt;Investing:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to clarify first what I mean by investing. The word has many meanings in our culture, so it’s time to be accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investing is about renouncing now to a certain amount of purchasing power, in the hope to receive back more purchasing power in the future.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, let’s see two or three examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buying a car, while often expensive, is not an investment. Its value depreciate quickly over time and is never gained back. It could be an investment if you use the car to perform activities that brings in significant money (ex: you buy a truck and transform it in food truck.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By the same token, just because something is expensive does not mean it is an investment. You need to have reasonable hope of at least getting back your purchasing power to name it that way. Think about it the next time a friend tells you he &lt;em&gt;invested&lt;/em&gt; in this brand new TV-set.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On the other hand, buying a diversified portfolio of shares with a long term horizon, has historically proven to generate a compounded return of 7% to 8 % per annum. After 10 years, such a portfolio will double in value. That’s what i call an improved purchasing power!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;productive-assets&quot;&gt;Productive Assets:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we are clear with the meaning of &lt;em&gt;investing&lt;/em&gt;, you need to figure out in what to invest your savings. There are many different assets available, and this can be very confusing. But as a rule of thumb, invest in productive assets, i.e. assets whose underlyings are producing cash flows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As we have seen, stocks are productive assets. They represent a shared ownership in a business, and this business is supposed to make profits by selling goods or services to customers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rental Real Estate is a productive asset: it generates cash flows to the owner by renting the housing unit to a tenant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gold is not really a productive asset. It has a nice property: it keeps its value. Over the long term, an ounce of gold in 1800 provided as much purchasing power as an ounce of gold now. There are of course fluctuations in between, but you get the picture. The downside of gold is that over the long term it won’t really increase your purchasing power&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cryptocurrencies are not (yet) productive assets. We haven’t found yet a stable way to use crypto-currencies that would entice customers to pay for. Sure, the value of Bitcoin and Co. has fluctuated a lot in the last few years. But at this stage it is still more speculation than a true productive asset.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-repeat-until-your-assets-are-producing-enough-cash-to-cover-your-expenses&quot;&gt;3) Repeat until your assets are producing enough cash to cover your expenses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much is enough to cover your needs? There is a lot of debates on the exact amount, but the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trinity_study&quot;&gt;Trinity Study&lt;/a&gt;  is a good starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published in 1998, the study defines a “safe withdrawal rate”, equal to 4% of your assets. Imagine someone withdrawing only 4% of his funds every year, while keeping the rest invested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;According to the study, such a person would have a 97% chance of never running out of money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gave birth to the &lt;em&gt;4% rule&lt;/em&gt; :  to be financially free your annual expenses should be less than 4% of your capital. Another way to state it is that your capital should be worth at least 25 times your annual expenses (because 25 = 1/4%).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is currently a lot of controversy about the validity of the Trinity Study, and people usually recommend to be a bit more conservative a save up to 33 times your annual expenses. For more details, you can consult the outstanding work of &lt;a href=&quot;https://earlyretirementnow.com/2016/12/07/the-ultimate-guide-to-safe-withdrawal-rates-part-1-intro/&quot;&gt;Early Retirement Now&lt;/a&gt; on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But yeah, if you don’t want to overcomplicate things, target a capital equal to around 25 and 30 times your annual spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that you know what is your target, this opens the room for many questions! How long does it take? How much should you save? What is the impact of the yield of your assets?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hem. It’s time for some maths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(if you are maths-phobic, you can directly jump to the remarks.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-maths-behind-all-of-that&quot;&gt;The maths behind all of that&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let’s call C0 your initial capital (i.e your current savings).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each year, you will save an amount S.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your annual expenses are E. You will thus want to reach an capital target T equal to 25 * E&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your investments have a yearly rate of return of r%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s call C(n) your capital at year n. Obviously, C(0) is equal to C0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After one year, C0 is invested in productive assets returning r%, and you have saved as well an additional S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C(1) = (1+r)  C_0 + S&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the same way, after an additional year, C(1) had returns of r%, and you saved yet another S&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C(2) = (1+r)  C(1) + S = (1+r)  [ (1+r)  C_0 + S ] + S&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C(n+1) = (1+r)  C(n) + S&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can show by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mathematical_induction&quot;&gt;mathematical induction&lt;/a&gt; that C(n) can be rewritten:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C(n) = (1+r) ^n  (C_0 + \frac {S}{r})  - \frac {S}{r}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At year N, C(N) reaches the target capital T ( equal to 25 times E)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C(N) = T = (1+r) ^N  (C0 + \frac {S}{r})  - \frac {S}{r}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solving for N, we get:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;N =  \frac  {\ln(  \frac  {T +\frac {S}{r}}  {(C_0 + \frac {S}{r}}) }{ \ln (1+r) }&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. If you start without any capital, you can simplify with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;N =  \frac  {\ln( 1 + \frac  {r T }{S} )}  { \ln (1+r) }&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing that    $ \frac{T}{S} =  \frac {25 E}{S}$   , we can introduce the concept of saving rate, which is equal to the ratio between your savings and your revenues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\sigma = \frac {Savings}{Revenues} = \frac {Savings}{Savings + Expenses } = \frac {S}{S + E }&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We show that   $ \frac{E}{S} =  (\frac {1}{\sigma} - 1) $&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and thus, our final result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;N =  \frac  {\ln( 1 + 25 r (\frac  {1 }{\sigma}-1))}  { \ln (1+r) }&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;remarks&quot;&gt;Remarks:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It does not look like a lot but it is actually huge. Knowing only your investment yield and your saving rate (i.e how much of your revenue are you saving), you can figure out how long it takes to be financially independent. Nothing else matters except these two variables!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Let’s see how long it takes to reach FI with different values of investment yields and saving rates:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/NSavingRate.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Results&quot; /&gt;
Someone saving half of his income and investing it at a 10% annual rate will be financially independent in 13 years. With the same annual returns, someone saving only 10% of his income will only reach financial freedom in 33 years! This is not a reasonable timeframe. Even less so if annual returns are less than 10%… The time needed to reach FI jumps then very quickly to over 50 years…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As you can see, the two conditions needed to reach financial freedom within 15 years are an annual investment returns of more than 5% and a saving rate of more than 50%!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s enough theory for today, dear reader!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spend way less that you earn, invest the difference in productive assets, rinse and repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s only the starting point. I discovered quickly that I would soon be asking more qualitative questions…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>julien</name></author><category term="featured" /><category term="sticky" /><summary type="html">As every journey starts somewhere, mine began when I discovered the concept of Financial Independence (See About). As such, this is the perfect topic to kickstart this website! What is Financial Independence? How do we define it? How to reach it? How long does it take?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://fooltowise.com/assets/images/ParrotLong.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://fooltowise.com/assets/images/ParrotLong.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>